Prakash Kumar Mahato

Date of Birth: 30th November 1980

Mobile: 8674843458

E-mail: prakash30nov@yahoo.com

https://in.linkedin.com/pub/prakash-kumar-mahato/a8/726/7a

Kalipahari, Maithon Post- Maithon

Dhanbad (828207) Jharkhand

Profile:

I am an enthusiastic, with more than 7+ years' experience in IT & Services (6 years in Education Management and 2.5 years in BPO). I have a proven track record in:

- Sales Management
- IT Operations and Infrastructure Management
- Business Development
- Key Account Management

Quick study with an ability to rapidly achieve organizational integration, easily assimilate job requirements and aggressively employ new methodologies. A good Team Management and coordination with the other concern departments in the organization for best service delivery.

Objective:

To use my technical and management skills in a challenging environment and to bring maximum output and profit to the company by delivering quality deliverables and thereby gaining satisfied customers.

Specialties:

Sales , Business development, Pre-Post sales client servicing, Client retention, Presentation skills, Relation management skills, Training, Quick learner, Decision making skills, Excellent communication, Sales promotions, Product branding, Competitor analysis

Technical Qualifications:

2004 - Microsoft Certified Professional (MCP) Paper: 070-210 Validation #: 383203875

Professional Training:

2008 CCNA from Genius .Com

2004 A+ with Networking & MCSE 2000 from ASSET International (High end Division of APTECH)

2001 Certificate in Information Technology from CMC (Computer Maintenance Corporation)

Education:

2014 BCA

2003 B.Com

1999 Intermediate (I.Com)

1997 ICSE

Employment History:

1. Business Development Manager at Next Education India Pvt. Ltd. July 2015 - Present.

- To provide ICT base solution to schools like (**Digital classrooms, ERP, Technology based Labs**), Handled 10 districts in Jharkhand (Base: Dhanbad)
- Cold Calls, Presentation, Proposal, Negotiation, Signup, Account Management & collection, up sell and cross sell.
- Utilize networking skills to build list of prospects to contact for new business.
- Track customers and prospects in CRM system including records of all contact.
- Visit customer locations to provide presentations to Teachers and Management.
- Develop a business plan and sales strategy for the market that ensures attainment of company sales goals and profitability.
- Serve additional role as Solution Consultant to clients leveraging thorough knowledge of company and competitor software.
- Oversee product sales lifecycle from closing to delivery through Operation support.

E-Learning Support Engineer at Next Education India Pvt. Ltd. December 2014 – June 2015.

School Learning Solutions is a pioneering & long initiative of Next Education. We at Next Education are committed to conceive innovative solutions in IT enabled learning for K-12 space & thus bring back the joy of learning to young minds. Today Next Education portfolio consists of a holistic range of futuristic solutions like Interactive Classrooms to empower teachers, with products like **TeachNext**, **Next Lab**, **Next ERP** and many more...

Responsibility:

- IT Support & Service
- Ensure 100% compliance towards service delivery as per the SLA
- Collection
- Cross Functional department co-ordination(Sales, Operation, SCM)
- Asset Management
- Software Update Management (SUM)
- Client Management
- Vendor Management
- Maintaining Time lines to deliver reports to HO
- CRM updation

2. IT Head at MyconInfotech Pvt. Ltd. (BPO) May 2012 - November 2014

As IT Head I am responsible for Planning and Implementation & Budgeting of overall IT Infrastructure. Acted as **Process Head** in new hiring, minimize attrition and Training session & Sales, in Telesales Process of Kotak Mahindra Insurance and Birla Sunlife Insurance.

Responsibility:

- Supervised and performed installation of new IT network infrastructure.
- LAN implementation with TCP/IP configuration and administration of 50 Users.
- Supported and maintained PRI- E1 with Dialer (CONTAQUE TM).
- Firewall implementation and configuration (WATCHGUARD TM).
- Coordinate with vendors like Airtel &TATA Tele Service for quick recovery of service.
- Account Management with vendors.
- Managed and Administered Windows XP and Windows 7 workstations and Laptops.
- Supported and maintained servers and backups with Log Reports.
- Administered creation of IT accounts & supported Microsoft Office 2003/2007.
- Managing Domains and Webmail, CRM.
- Utilized problem solving and troubleshooting abilities to resolve any major issues.
- Provided employee training and instructions (through presentations) regarding basic operation of software and hardware, technical support and quality standards.
- Updated management on a regular basis through reports and presentations
- Shared knowledge with new recruits.
- Maintained company peripheral network devices regularly, including printers and scanners and routine maintenance.
- Tested the IT networking systems, monitored the performance of network servers and maintained firm's computer systems.
- Planned and executed routine repairs and system upgrades.
- Made use of helpdesk systems to prioritize work-load and update queries and calls.
- Documented and maintained supply of all required inventory.
- Setting up meeting for performance targets for speed, efficiency, sales and quality;
- Liaising with supervisors, team leaders, operatives and third parties to gather information and resolve issues;
- Monitoring calls to improve quality minimize errors and track performance;

3. Faculty cum Centre Head at Genius.Com (Franchisee of IIHT & Study Centre Sikkim Manipal University) April 2007 – April 2012.

Handling batches, managing centre administration, managing marketing activities of centre, making corporate tie-ups with the IT companies and giving placement to the students. Handling student management and relationship and monitoring of students attendance, giving feedback and taking corrective measures to ensure proper attendance of students. Develop the team and keep them aligned to the mission and vision of centre.

Ensure Marketing activities such as leaflets, hoardings, kiosks, banners, posturing in different areas of district and adjoining district. Throughout the year student enrolment was more than 350. Develop market-monitoring, strategy, seminars, and others for business development. Hold the credit of getting highest turnover among all franchises under Sikkim Manipal University in Jharkhand.

Notable Achievement Promoted as Head of Department for **IIHT** and our center won Bharat Ratna Award from **Governor of Jharkhand** for outstanding performance in Education in the year 2009.

Ensure that all the documents and records are maintained properly at the centre and as per the laid down procedures. Ensure timely submission and accuracy in Centre MIS reports. Track competitive activity and market trends and report to findings to the management on a regular basis.

Skills & Expertise:

Sales
New Business Development
Sales Management
Lead Generation
CRM
E-Learning
ERP
Technical Support
Service Delivery
Microsoft Certified Professional

OTHER INFORMATION:

Nationality	:	Indian.
Language	:	English, Hindi, Bengali
Hobbies	:	Playing cricket.
PLACE		
DATE		